Back in Lecture 5, I promised we'd get to the integer ALU operations for multiplication
and division later in the semester.
Well, we have arrived.
We are going to discuss three different algorithms for integer multiplication, array, multi-cycle,
and boost encoding.
This will do two algorithms for integer division, restoring and non-restoring.
Let's focus on unsigned integer multiplication first.
Jump back to grade school and work out this base two binary example.
Starting with the least significant bit of the multiplier, you multiply the entire multiple
can.
This is the first row of partial products.
In this example, we're going to multiply one thousand times one.
This gives us one thousand as the first partial sum.
Now you can do bit one of the multiplier times eight, and the result goes into partial sums
shifted left one.
Same for bit two, although shifted left two.
Here the MSB of the multiplier is a one, which we multiply by the multiple can eight, and
this partial sum is inserted, shifted left three.
Once you have the four partial sums, you sum down the columns, carrying when necessary,
and you're done.
Multiplying two four-bit numbers produces eight bits, which includes a potential carry
from the last partial sum.
This pattern holds.
Multiplying two 32-bit numbers produces a 64-bit result.
This is a more formal presentation of each bit in the partial sums.
The brute force way of implementing integer multiplication is using an array multiplier.
You simply instantiate a basic cell per bitwise partial product, as shown here.
Each cell consists of an AND gate to multiply two input bits from the multiple canned A
and the multiplier B.
This partial product is then added to the partial sums from the cell above and the carry
from the upper right diagonal.
These basic cells can then be composed into larger multipliers.
The example here shows 16-bit multiplication.
The basic cells make up all of the rows with the exception of the topmost and bottommost.
The topmost row can be implemented with just half adders, and each half adder takes in
two partial products from the input operands.
The bottommost row of adders simply accumulates all of the partial sums that have cascaded
down from all of the partial products.
So this organization is purely combinational and conceptually straightforward.
However, the required hardware is very expensive, requiring many, many adders.
And considering that nonpowers of two integer multiplications can be quite rare in real applications,
this ends up wasting a lot of chip real estate.
Instead of spending so many hardware resources on such a rare operation, we can also opt
to build multi-cycle multipliers instead.
The idea is to accumulate the partial products row by row.
For each bit of the multiplier, we compute the partial product.
Since we're dealing with binary, this is a simple conditional add.
If the multiplier bit is 1, then we add the multiple can to the accumulated sum, otherwise
we do nothing.
Then we shift the multiple can and move on to the next bit of the multiplier, repeating
the process.
This is a simple hardware organization of a 32-bit multi-cycle multiplier.
We have three registers.
The multiplier uses only a 32-bit register.
But considering that the final product needs 64 bits, the multiple can and product are
each stored in a 64-bit register, and we perform the accumulation with a 64-bit ALU.
Let's now walk through an example of how the multiplier operates.
To simplify things, we'll go through the 4x4 multiplication example that we saw earlier.
The registers are initialized with the multiple can and multiplier values, and the product
is initialized to 0.
Then we just follow the process described earlier.
We look at each bit of the multiplier, starting at the least significant.
In this case, it's a 1.
That means we should add the multiple can with the current product.
Then we move on to the next bit by shifting the multiplier right and shifting the multiple
can left.
In this case now, the least significant bit of the multiplier is 0, so that means we
don't add, and the product is unchanged.
Then we shift again, the multiplier bit is 0 again, so no change to the product.
Then we shift to the last bit, and it's a 1, so we add the current multiple can value
to the product.
In the end, we've shifted out all of the multiplier bits, which signals a done signal
in the control logic.
The product register now contains the final result.
Though straightforward and designed, the implementation is not very efficient.
It requires a large 64-bit ALU to perform the accumulation, but when you think about
it, we really only need to add 32 bits at a time.
You can visually see this in the 4x4 example in the top right.
Even though we're accumulating an 8-bit product, the individual partial products are
only 4 bits each.
So we can improve the multiplier by instead of shifting the multiple can left each time,
we can just shift the product right.
So now we only need a 32-bit ALU and 32-bit multiple can register.
And this time, all of the partial sums are added into the most significant half of the
product register.
With this now, you're probably wondering, where did the multiplier go?
Since we're only accumulating into the left half of the product register, we can actually
initialize the right half with the multiplier.
If you recall, we also shift the multiplier right each time, so it fits nicely in the
product register.
Now let's see how this improved multiplier operates using the same 4x4 example as before.
The left half of the product register is initialized to zero, while the right half is initialized
to the multiplier.
As before, we look at each bit in the multiplier one by one.
The first bit is a one, which adds the multiple canned into the left half of the product register.
Then the entire product register is logically shifted right by one.
The next bit of the multiplier is zero, so nothing is added.
Then we shift once more, and the next bit is zero again.
Then we get to the final bit, which is one, so we add the multiple canned.
Upon the last shift, the multiplier is gone, and the product register contains the final
product.
Note that the number of ALU instructions is equal to the number of ones in the multiplier
value, so for values with a lot of ones, particularly negative values, the multiplication
operand can take a lot of cycles.
Now what happens if we want to multiply negative numbers?
So far, we've only looked on unsigned multiplication.
To handle signed numbers, the most straightforward option is to convert the operands into positive
integers first, multiply them, then convert the product to negative if one of the inputs
is negative.
A better option would be to simply use the improved multi-cycle multiplier design that
we just discussed, except replace all of the logic shift writes with aromatic write shifts.
Then if the multiplier is negative, follow the same procedure for all bits except the
most significant bit of the multiplier.
For the MSB, subtract the multiple canned from the left half of the product register
instead of adding.
An efficient way of performing multiplication is to use Booth's algorithm.
Recall the trick for multiplying numbers by 9.
You first multiply the number by 10 instead, and then just subtract the number once, as
shown in this example for multiplying 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 by 9.
This reduces the computation from adding 6 partial products to just a single shift and
subtraction operation.
Booth's multiplier works off the same principle.
For example, multiplying a number by 120 in decimal is equivalent to multiplying it
by 128 minus 8.
This involves less operations compared to adding up four partial products since there
were four 1 bits in 120.
To realize Booth's multiplication algorithm, we must first encode the multiplier to Booth's
encoding.
This is just another way of representing signed integers.
The goal is to convert each run of 1s in the multiplier into a difference of powers
of 2, as in the example above where the run of 4 1s in 120 can be represented as 128 minus
8.
This slide shows an example of Booth's encoding and multiplication algorithm.
As before, we start from the rightmost, least significant bit and walk through each of the
bits.
Whenever we see a rising edge, as in a transition from 0 to 1, then we encode a negative sign,
which means we should subtract the multiple can from the current product at this bit position.
Whenever we see a falling edge, as in a transition from 1 to 0, then we encode a positive sign,
which means we need to add the multiple can at this bit position.
In all other cases, when we're in the middle of a run of 1s or a run of 0s, we do nothing.
The bottom shows the notation for Booth's encoding, showing how the number 120 is represented
with a negative sign at bit position 3 and a positive sign at bit position 7, which is
another way of saying that the number 120 is composed of negative 2 to the third, which
is minus 8, plus positive 2 to the seventh, which is 128.
Let's see how Booth's multiplier operates.
Taking an example, with multiple can of negative 6 and a multiplier of positive 6, which is
represented in Booth's encoding as plus 0, minus 0 from left to right.
At this point is actually a similar procedure as before.
We start by looking at the least significant bit of the multiplier, except in Booth's encoding.
The first bit is 0, which means that we don't add the multiple can to the product.
Then we shift the multiple can and look at the next bit of the multiplier, which is a
minus sign.
This means that we need to subtract the multiple can, now negative 12, from the current product
0, which is 0 minus the negative 12, which leaves the value 12 in the product.
Then we shift again and find that the next bit is 0, so we don't do anything.
Then we get to the last bit, which is a plus sign, so that means we add the multiple can,
which at this point is negative 48.
This results in a final sum of negative 36 in the product register.
The takeaway is that unlike our previous multiplier design, the number of ALU operations is equal
to the number of falling and rising edges in the multiplier value, as opposed to the number
of ones.
In a lot of cases, but not all, this can be more efficient.
Let's move on to integer division.
We'll be focusing only on unsigned division here.
The simplest way to extend to signed division is to divide the magnitudes and correct the
sign of the quotient.
So the way we learned back in grade school was to perform long division.
At each bit or digit position of the dividend, starting from left most significant side,
we try to subtract the divisor from the subset of bits.
Only if the divisor fits, that is, it's less than the dividend bits.
Only then do we actually subtract.
In this case, we set the corresponding quotient bit to one.
Then we take the remainder and continue the process with the rest of the dividend bits
until we've gone through all the bits.
To implement division and hardware, we effectively try to follow the same long division procedure.
The most straightforward implementation is to employ restoring division.
At each bit position, we need to check if the divisor fits.
With restoring division, we subtract the divisor each time.
If the resulting remainder is less than zero, then we know that the divisor did not fit,
so we restore it by adding the divisor back.
Then we move on to the next bit position and continue this process until the end of the
dividend.
This is a simple hardware organization of 32-bit restoring division.
As with multiplication, the result of 32-bit division is 64 bits consisting of a 32-bit
quotient and a 32-bit remainder.
We need three registers, one for the divisor, one for the quotient, and one for the remainder
that's initially set to the dividend.
Let's walk through how it works using an 8-bit example.
The divisor is initialized to the left half of the divisor register with the rest as zeros.
The remainder is initialized with the dividend value.
So first thing we do is subtract the divisor from the current value in the remainder register.
Then we check to see if the remainder is greater than or equal to zero.
In this case, it's not, so we left-shift into zero into the quotient.
Since the divisor doesn't fit, we need to restore it by adding the divisor back to the
remainder register.
This continues in the same way for the next four-bit positions, so we'll skip ahead.
So now the divisor has been shifted right four times and the quotient has four zeros in it.
As before, we perform the subtraction, but this time the remainder is actually positive.
So this means that the divisor fit, so we push in a one into the quotient and now we
don't need to restore.
We shift the divisor and move on to the next bit now.
Again we subtract the divisor.
This time it doesn't fit, so we shift a zero into the quotient and consequently restore
the remainder by adding the divisor back into it.
Then we skip ahead to the last bit position.
We perform the subtraction and find that the divisor fits this time, so we shift a one into
the quotient.
Since we don't need to restore, the division is now complete and the final results can
be found in the quotient and remainder registers.
There are a couple ways to improve upon this simple implementation.
First of all, we can skip the first subtraction operation.
Since the remainder is initially zero, there's really no point in subtracting because the
divisor will never fit, so instead we can change the algorithm to shift first then subtract.
This works similar to before, except we need to do an extra shift in the end as we'll show
in the next few slides.
Second, we can improve the design in a similar way that we improved the multiplier from earlier.
Fundamentally, we're only ever adding or subtracting 32 bits at a time, so we should
be able to just use a 32-bit ALU.
We can also reduce the number of registers by storing the quotient into the remainder
register, saving an additional register.
This is the organization of the improved division.
Now instead of right-shifting the divisor each time, we instead left-ship the remainder
register.
As before, the right half of the remainder initially holds the dividend value, but as
we shift the remainder register to the left each time, we can actually insert the quotient
bits into it, then in the end, the left half will hold the remainder value while the right
half holds the quotient value.
So as mentioned, we skip the first subtraction since the divisor will never fit, so we left-shift
the remainder register and shift into zero as the first bit of the quotient.
Then from here on, we follow a similar procedure as before.
At each bit position, we first subtract the divisor from the left half of the remainder
register.
Since the resulting remainder is not positive, then we perform an addition to restore.
Finally, we shift into zero for the quotient since the divisor did not fit.
Let's skip ahead by four bits now.
Again we perform the subtraction, but this time the remainder is greater than zero, so
we do not need to restore.
We simply shift in a one into the quotient and then move on.
Let's skip ahead to the last bit position.
We perform the subtraction and then find that the remainder is positive, so again, no restoration
needs to be performed.
We simply need to shift in a one to the quotient.
So now we've gone through all the bits of the dividend, but before we finish up, because
we skipped the first subtraction, we now have to right-shift the left half of the remainder
as a correction, and now the final result can be found in the remainder register.
Though straightforward, this implementation can be quite inefficient since it requires
two ALU cycles per bit position, one to perform the subtraction to check if the divisor fits,
and one to perform the addition if restore is needed.
We can improve on this by implementing non-restoring division.
To do this, we start off similar to before.
We first subtract the divisor from the remainder, but this time, if the remainder is negative,
we won't restore right away.
The correct remainder at this current bit position i is supposed to be whatever is in
the remainder register plus the divisor due to restoration.
So that means that the correct remainder after the next position i plus one would be equal
to whatever is in the remainder register plus the divisor shifted left by one minus the divisor.
Expanding on this, we find that it simply equals whatever is in the remainder register
right now plus the divisor.
So this implies that at each bit position, if the remainder is less than zero, that instead
of subtracting the divisor next time, we actually need to add it instead.
So let's see how this works.
The hardware organization is similar to before, and the registers are initialized in the same
way as before.
Just like in the improved restoring division, we start off by left shifting in a zero into
the remainder register as shown.
Then the first thing we do is subtract the divisor from the left half of the remainder
as usual.
We find that the resulting remainder is not positive, but instead of restoring now, we
simply left shift in a zero into the quotient and set a flag that says at the next bit position,
we will add the divisor instead of subtracting it.
And that's just what we do.
We add the divisor into the remainder register.
Again we check if the resulting remainder is positive.
It's still negative, so we left shift in another zero and specify that we will perform add
again on the next bit position.
The same thing happens for the next three bits, so we'll skip ahead.
At this bit position, we add the divisor.
This time, we find that the remainder is positive.
So we left shift in a one into the quotient and specify that the next operation will be
a subtraction instead.
Let's skip ahead again to the last bit position.
Here we need to perform an addition again, so we add the divisor into the left half
of the remainder register.
We find that the remainder is positive.
So we just left shift in a one into the quotient.
And now we've reached the end of the dividend.
But just like before, we need to right shift the left half of the remainder register once
just to correct the remainder.
And we have finished.
Let's end this lecture with a quick example of 4-bit boost multiplication.
Consider a multiplicand of negative 6 and a multiplier of negative 2.
Compute the booth encoding of the multiplier.
Enlist the partial products of the boost multiplication.
Please take some time now to work through it.
The booth encoding for the multiplier is 0, 0 minus 0.
So the first partial product is simply the multiplicand times 0.
The next partial product shifts the multiplicand by 1 and multiplies it by negative 1.
And the last two partial products are shown simply multiplying by 0.
Adding these up yields the final product of 12.